Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees Union Local 5 and Stern Brothers Arbitration Transcript 5126
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees Union Local 5 and Stern Brothers Arbitration Transcript
1948
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Carter, Edward W.
American Arbitration Association (AAA)
5126
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Proceedings, transcripts.
Consist of transcripts and exhibits in department store arbitration cases between New York City locals of the United Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees and Stern Brothers, heard by Paul Raymond Hays, and with Gimbel Brothers Department Store, heard by Edward W. Carter.
3337308
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 24, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The United Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees had its beginnings as an aggressive union which evolved out of the venerable but conservative Retail Clerks International Association and the Congress of Industrial Organizations' Department Store Organizing Committee in the 1930s.
In the period 1937-1940, the union, then known as the United Retail Employees of America, made major gains in New York City which included not only organizing the large department stores there, but also establishing a forty hour week for retail clerks in the city. A right-left struggle over the leadership of the union was dormant during World War II, only to arise with new violence in 1948. This internecine rivalry resulted in a decline in the union, to the benefit of its old rival, the Retail Clerks International Association. In 1954, the union's name changed to the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union.
Scope and Contents
Consists of transcripts and exhibits in department store arbitration cases between New York City locals of the United Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees and Stern Brothers, heard by Paul Raymond Hays, and with Gimbel Brothers Department Store, heard by Edward W. Carter.
Documents in the Stern Brothers case consist of the transcript of the arbitration proceedings (9 vol.) and exhibits (49) submitted by the company and by Local 5 of the union, describing department store wages, hours of work, and working conditions. The issues involved in this case include entry level wages and group health insurance.
The Gimbel Brothers case file contains transcripts of the arbitration proceedings between the company and Local 2 (7 vol.). Issues in this case include minimum level of wages, position classification, job status, and a dispute over contract language regarding discharge.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3012: Alice Cook Papers /3052: John W. McConnell Papers /4212: Kheel Center Current Documents Correspondence 5012: Saul Wallen Papers 5129: Maxwell Copelof Arbitration Briefs, Exhibits, Transcripts and Decisions 5131: Sidney A. Wolff Arbitration Files 5206-D: Local 1199 Drug Division Records 5206-G: Local 1199 Guild Division Records 5206-PR: Local 1199 President Leon Davis Records 5206-S: Local 1199 Executive Secretary Moe Foner Records 5206-X: Local 1199 Clippings and News Releases 5216: Theresa Wolfson Papers 5257 AV: Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees Union Audio-Visual Materials 5275: AFL-CIO Internal Disputes Plan Decisions of the Impartial Umpire 5305: Benjamin H. Wolf Papers 5311: NWLB Region II Office Files and Cases 5473: Ralph D. Winstead Papers 5493: Elmer E. Hilpert Arbitration Papers 5505: Samuel Wolchok Correspondence and Minutes 5510: Local 1199 Records 5525: Local 1199 Additional Files 5538: James C. Hill Arbitration Files 5539: Benjamin H. Wolf Additional Arbitration Files 5576: S. Stanley Alderfer Arbitration Files 5583/1: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 1 5588: David L. Cole Papers 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5651: Local 1199 Additional Records 5663 mf: Collective Bargaining Agreements on Microfilm 5680 OH: Local 1199 Oral History Project 5697: James A. Gross Arbitration Files 5724 mf: Cigar Makers International Union Records on Microfilm 5733: Peter Seitz Arbitration Files 5780/002: ILGWU David Dubinsky Correspondence 5780/203: ILGWU Jay Mazur Papers 5803: Benjamin Wolf Additional Arbitration Files
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Clerks (Retail trade); Work assignments -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union; Stern Brothers Department Store; United Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees of America; Carter, Edward W.; Hays, Paul R.(Paul Raymond), 1903-; Gimbel Brothers, Inc.
3337308
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 1, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 2, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 3, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 4, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail. Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 5, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 6, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 7, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Arbitration between Local 5, Retail, Wholesale, & Department Store Employees Union and Stern Brothers Vol. 8, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel - Local 2 September 21, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Arbitration Gimbel's - Local 2 Sept. 20, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel Bros. and Local 2, CIO August 30th, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel's - Local October 18th, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel - Local 2 October 12, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel Bros. Local #2 September 29, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Minutes of Arbitration Gimbel - Local 2 October 14, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)